hey what's up guys my name is achernar
and welcome back to my say boss boss
series so today we're gonna be talking
all about memory and in fact we're gonna
be talking about two different types of
memory in C++ the stack and the heap
which you may have heard a lot about and
might not be a hundred central and what
that means why they're used when they're
used and how all that works and why you
even care about how that works okay so
first of all the second of heat what are
they well when our program starts it
gets divided into a bunch of different
like areas of memory and there's a lot
more than just a stack in the heap but
the two kind of ones that we care about
most I would say would be the stack and
the heap now in terms of how application
is launched and what the operating
system does is loosely it will load the
entire program into memory as well as
allocate a whole bunch of physical RAM
so that our actual application can run
now the stack and the heap are two areas
that we actually have in our RAM the
stack is typically an area of memory
that has a predefined size usually
around two megabytes or so and the heap
is an area that is also kind of
predefined to a default value however it
can grow and change as our application
goes on now it's important to note that
the actual location the physical
location of these two areas of memory is
ultimately the same it's in our Ram a
lot of people tend to think that the
stack might be something that's stored
in the CPU cache or something like that
whilst it is likely to be hot in the
case because we're continually accessing
it that's we can't like not all of it
will be stored in our cache and that's
not how any of that works so just keep
in mind that the actual location of
those two areas of memory is in our
memory right that's why they're two
different areas of our memory now memory
in our program is used so that we can
actually store data we need a place to
store the data that we need to run our
program whether that be local variables
or maybe we've read stuff in from a file
and we need to process that data all
that kind of stuff we need a place to
store that and the stack in the heap
they are areas in which we're allowed to
store data now they work very very
differently but fundamentally what they
do is the same we can ask C++ to give us
some memory from either the stack or the
heap and it will give us a block of
memory of our requested size if
everything
as well the difference is how it
allocates that memory for us so suppose
for an example that we want to be able
to store an integer an integer on most
platforms is 4 bytes an int right so how
do we find a contiguous block of 4 bytes
of memory contiguous just means in a row
right how do we find that block of 4
bytes of memory the way that the stack
will give us that memory versus the way
that the heap will give us that memory
that's different and when we asked for
memory like that that's called the
memory allocation or just an allocation
for sure so let's take a look at some of
the differences between allocating and
ant and maybe various other kind of
pieces of data on the stack versus the
heap in our actual C++ code so I'm going
to show you how to allocate three
different types of data over here in our
program first of all we'll start off
with an int so I'll just write int value
equals 5 that's it that's how you
allocate an integer on the stack and in
fact we're also giving it the value 5 if
we were to do this on the heap it would
look like this in pointer H I'll say H
value 4 heat value equals new int and
then we have to dereference that H value
and give it the value 5 ok so you can
notice that it is two lines of code but
more importantly we actually use the new
keyword here to allocate on the heap
that's what kind of distinguishes these
two allocations that is a stack
allocation and this is a heap allocation
with arrays it's kind of similar we have
int array and then 5 for example for
five elements in the array and on the
heap this would look like this in H
array for heap array equals new int five
like that so again the major difference
being where we're using the new keyword
here to actually allocate that memory
and then finally I'll show you a quick
example with an object so if I make a
struct here or a class doesn't really
matter called vector three and this will
just have three floats X Y Z if I was to
allocate this on the stack it would look
like this vector three vector and on the
heap it would look like this vector
three pointer H vector equals new vector
3 and these parentheses are of course
optional but I like to keep them in now
before I run this application and step
through and show you how it actually
works let's actually give these these
variables of ours default values so this
inner ray has absolutely nothing right
now so let's maybe give it some values
I'll say array 0 equals 1 and then let's
also give these just ascending numbers 2
3 4 5 that should be easy enough to see
I'm going to copy and paste this and
same for our age array making sure that
I of course type in age here and then
for our vector I'm just going to use the
default constructor here to actually
give it some values so we'll say X will
be 10 by default and Y will be 11 and Z
will be 12
now these are floats so they might look
a little bit different in memory but it
should be okay all right cool so now so
now let's put a breakpoint over here and
hit f5 so the first thing I'm going to
do is actually go to the memory address
of values to fight type an ampersand
value in my memory view over here you
can access the memory view by going to
debug windows memory and then memory one
you can see that it takes me to the
memory address of that variable now
ccccc in debug mode means that we just
haven't actually initialized that value
yet so if I hit f10 you can see that we
change to five so now we have that value
in our actual memory pretty simple now
let's hit f10 and see where this array
actually is so I'm just gonna type in a
right order to use a pointer cuz it's an
array we'll see where we are okay pretty
cool so we have one here let's hit f10
and then again and then again and then
again okay cool so check that out we
have one two three four five in our
memory all in a row brilliant now if we
look over a few bytes we also have five
over here right and that five happens to
be our value five so if I go to the
memory address of value once more you
can see that if I scroll up just a
little bit that's my value and that is
my actual array so they're right next to
each other now there are some bytes in
between the two that's just because
we're running in debug mode it's
actually just adding safety guards kind
of around all about variables to make
sure that we don't overflow them or
access them in the wrong memory address
and all that kind of stuff
and finally we have our vector so if I
hit f10 and then I look at the actual
memory address of our vector you can see
there over here we have 0 to 0 for 100
ah basically we have our 12 bytes here
that represents our vector a bunch of
safety guards and then the 1 2 3 4 5
array and then that 5 variable so it's
all really kind of close together in
memory because what actually happens is
when we allocate variables in the stack
all it happens is the stack pointer that
is the pointer of like the top of the
stack
basically just moves moves that amount
of bytes so if I want to allocate an
integer that's 4 bytes we move the stack
pointer 4 bytes
said if I want to allocate an array like
we have here five integers that's four
times five or twenty 20 bytes the stack
pointer moves 20 bytes and finally for
our vector three we have three floats
each float is four bytes so 12 bytes we
just move the stack pointer that is it
the the memory is literally stored on
top of each other like a stack now in
most stack implementations we actually
grow the stack backwards which is why
you're seeing higher memory addresses
having like the first value so int value
is actually stored at a higher memory
address and then we kind of store the
the array next to it but kind of
backwards at a lower memory address
value and then because it kind of grows
backwards but the idea of a stack is we
literally just stack things on top of
each other which is why a stack
allocation is extremely fast
it's literally like one CPU instruction
all we do is we move the stack pointer
and then we return the address of that
stack pointer that's it so again I want
to allocate an integer that's four bytes
I move the stack pointer in this case
backwards four bytes and I return that
memory address because that is the
beginning of my block of 4 bytes that is
what a stack allocation is it's
extremely fast let's take a look at what
the heap allocation actually does so
there's not really much point in showing
you this because the memory is not
really gonna be close together but if we
just take a look at H value
you see we've we still of course get
five over here and then just in the kind
of middle of nowhere if you note the
address of this it's actually a 59 B b1
8 now if I look at my array and I take a
look at H array you can see it's at a
completely different memory address he
hasn't been initialized yet so if we had
F 10 a few times you can see of course
those variables do get set but that
address is 5 6 8 they're at the end and
H value is B b1 8 just completely
different areas of our memory so there's
not really much point in showing you
this memory of you anyway but what I do
want to mention is a few things about
this heap allocation first of all yes I
am using the new keyword here however if
you were using smart pointers and you
were using make unique or make shared
it's exactly the same thing it will call
new for you and then the other really
important thing of course is that you
actually have to delete memory
deallocate using new smart pointers will
do that for you but since we have used
new here we actually have to call delete
H value delete HRA
with the array delete operator here and
delete H vector as well so we do
actually have to manually free our
memory whereas with the stack as well
what happens is once this scope in which
you've allocated that stack memory
actually ends all of the memory that
you've allocated in that stack just gets
popped off it just gets freed so if we
were to do something like a wrap this in
a scope it can be any scope it can be
this function scope of this main
function or it can just be an empty
scope like this or like a for loop or a
while loop of an if statement whatever
any kind of scope when this scope comes
to an end everything that was allocated
on the stack inside that scope just gets
popped off it's just free to just go on
its reclaimed
because the stack just moves to the
position it was before we actually
entered this scope so that's another
really important difference between the
two the stack you kind of just get a
free free or in the sense that it
doesn't cost you anything to free any
memory because the stack just because
again freeing memory with the stack is
basically the same operation as
allocating it's just that instead of
moving our stack pointer backwards and
returning that address we just pop
everything off the stack so our stack
pointer goes back up to where it was
before the scope began and once if you
instruction it's basically free whereas
with delete that obviously has to
actually free everything now let's talk
a little bit about what the new key what
actually does now I do have a video on
this definitely check that out if you're
more interested in this kind of object
lifetime stuff as well I have made a
video about that as well so the object
lifetime video is more about how stack
allocations work and how we can kind of
you know use scopes to our advantage
when dealing with this automatic
deletion thing definitely recommend
checking it out as well in fact I'll
probably just leave a list of videos
over there in the top right corner so
that you can just check out anyway let's
just talk a little bit about how the
heap actually works and what new and
delete do so the new keyword will really
just call malloc a function called
malloc or memory allocate and what that
will do is in turn usually call the
underlying operating system like
platform specific function and that will
allocate memory for you on the heap and
the way that it does that is when you
say application you get a certain amount
of physical RAM kind of allocated to you
and your program will maintain something
called a free list which basically just
keeps track of which blocks of memory
are free and where they are and all that
so that when you actually ask for
dynamic memory zhing by dynamic memory a
memory when you ask for heap memory use
Mallett it will be able to kind of go
through the free list and be like oh
yeah I have a free block of memory that
is at least as big as what you've asked
for I will give you a pointer to that
and then I'll also record some things
such as the size of the allocation and
the fact that it's now allocated and you
can't use that block of memory anymore
there's a bunch of bookkeeping that goes
on and then you basically get that
pointer back now the actual
implementation of malloc is kind of
dependent on the implementation right I
have linked a few I've dropped some
links in the description if you want to
know more about exactly what malloc
doesn't how it works it's a fairly heavy
function there's a lot of bookkeeping
that needs to be done and you don't just
get your memory and to make things even
worse if you've asked for more memory
than is actually in that free list in
that initial kind of allocation that
your operating system is giving you then
your application your program has to
actually ask your operating system hey I
need some more memory please and that is
very expensive so there's that potential
cost which is huge really the point that
I'm trying to make here is that
allocating memory on the heap is a whole
thing whereas allocating memory on the
stack is like one CPU instruction that
is all I want you to take away from this
video really the fact that the
differences between these two are
primarily the allocation now you could
argue that the other benefit of
allocating memory on the stack or just
storing variables in the stack is the
fact that they're close together in
memory and therefore they can basically
fit onto one kind of CPU cache line if
we're looking at the actual code that
we've got here though I mean we're
talking about using the heap potentially
like a couple of cache misses verses in
the stack maybe we wouldn't get any
after we kind of request that first
stack variable we put something on to
the stack a couple of cache misses
versus no cache misses is like no big
deal at all you probably won't notice
the difference at all if we're dealing
with a couple of million of cache misses
right a couple million cache misses
that's a big deal but with a few cache
misses like if it's kind of you can't
really argue the point the the fact that
the memory is closer together on the
stack or the fact that the stack is
probably hot because you're continually
accessing is just just by keeping like
local bear
there and also putting stuff into
registers for when you pop functions
onto the stack and stuff like that
that's kind of a valid point but in the
real world and you probably won't notice
the difference because you're just not
getting enough cache misses for it to
actually make first actually cause a
problem
so the difference the big difference
between the two is the allocation the
allocation is the slow part allocating
memory on the stack is once if your
instruction in fact let's take a look at
the generators assembly behind what
we've just written and we can see what
it actually does I'm just going to
compile this code by hitting ctrl f7 in
my properties from my project I've also
just got under CC Plus last output files
I've got assembler output to assembly
with source code so that we can look at
it and here we have the assembly so
let's just go down to our value variable
okay so here's our code int value equals
5 that is the CPU instruction that it
runs now this is compiled and debug
won't keep that in mind so there may be
some extra things when it comes to the
heat comparison but the stack you can
see all the does is it moves five into a
register that's it done or specifically
into this kind of stack pointer add a
specific offset but the idea is that's
it it's once a few instruction now with
the array we kind of have two things
here and it actually does a bit of a
multiplication whatever I'm not going to
talk about the semantics of that but you
can see what it's really just done is
it's just allocated enough space for our
kind of array here and that's it you can
with I mean this is just setting
variables whatever and with our vector
allocation again it's called a
constructor over here but other than
that the allocation is actually just
immediate now here is our allocation on
the heap look at what that does the main
thing is it calls an entire operator and
that operate a new course malloc and
then that obviously has to go through
the free list and check to see if we've
got enough memory and get it the memory
and record the fact that it's now been
taken and how much has been allocated
and then we have to delete it off -
we're done the whole nightmare right and
if we keep reading you can see the same
thing obviously happens for the array
and then finally if we look at even
deleting the vector first of all it is
quite heavy and it does pull the
constructor of course the same as our
stack the delete is incredibly heavy as
well keep in mind this is compiled in
debug mode which is why you're seeing so
much code it would be a lot leaner in
release mode but still there's
going on here and then of course with a
regulating and linear vector we get a
bunch of stuff as well but again main
point being that allocating that value v
on the stack is just that that's all it
is right and of course if this was a
class that just had a bunch of integers
it would look the same the same
essentially right I mean you can see
that the vector allocation looks exactly
the same it's just cause the constructor
so I hope that all of that is kind of
clear to you the fact that you should
try and allocate on the stack whenever
possible the only reason really to
allocate on the heap is if you can't
allocate on the staff whether whether
you need that lifetime to actually be
longer than the scope of your function
or whatever scope you're dealing with or
you specifically need more data like I
want to load a texture that's 15
megabytes or something like that that's
not gonna fit onto the stack you'll have
to allocate that on the heap and all
that kind of stuff right but if you can
you should be allocated on the stack all
the time because it's like once if you
instruction and that's very very real
performance difference now one more time
just so that this is completely clear
the performance difference is the
allocation so if you were theoretically
to pre-allocate I don't know a full
gigabyte block of memory before you ran
your program on the heap and then you
were to kind of heap allocate from that
pre-allocated for like gigabyte block of
memory it would basically be the same
right the only thing you're potentially
dealing with there is again CPU cache
misses but there's probably not enough
of them to actually matter so the fact
that when you call new it has to go
through the free list and ask for memory
and book keep all of that that is the
slow part of the stack versus the heap
the actual access is usually negligible
right usually not always we might talk
more about CPU cache optimization and
stuff like that certainly if you're
writing through a collection of a
million elements and every single one of
them is a cache miss you're gonna see a
very real performance difference between
if you have everything kind of
contiguously or fragmented but that's a
nother video drop a comment if you want
to say that I think I'll make it because
that's probably something is very
interesting very interesting to a lot of
people but anyway that's about it for
this video
we're definitely going to learn more
about kind of allocating in the real
world and how we can minimize
allocations we'll have to spend quite a
bit of time discussing allocations when
we actually start out gaming into the
series because it's very important for
kind of real world applications
oh and by real world applications
between real time applications so it's
really important for games essentially
not to continuously allocate frame to
frame because that will be slow so we
have to basically come up with some
clever memory management techniques if
we want to our game engine to actually
be efficient which is why we will
definitely be discussing that in the
game engine series anyway I hope I hope
I've answered all of your kind of stack
first heap questions if I didn't drop a
comment below I'll maybe make a
follow-up video if I need to I think
that's about it there I mean really we
didn't go to in depth into how it
actually works on like an operating
system level but I think for most people
it's probably gonna be enough if you
enjoyed this video please hit the like
button you can also support this series
and everything that I do here on YouTube
by going to patronymic on course at the
Turner huge shout out to all of my
patrons there this video that you're
saying right now probably wouldn't exist
if it wasn't for them so again huge
thank you and there's a bunch of really
cool rewards that you did that you can
actually get if you go out there and you
help support this channel next time I
don't even know what we're gonna talk
about next time I've got a list but if
you guys want to see something specific
drop a comment below and just hit the
thumbs up button on any comment that you
like so that the kind of top rated
comments kind of go up to the top and
I'll see if I can make a video else cuz
it'll be that because I want to make
videos that you guys want to see I will
see you next time goodbye
[Music]